This is Hacker Public Radio Episode 4726, for 2026-09-14
Today's show is entitled, "Trurl's intro show"
The host is Trurl and the duration is 00:38:45
The flag is Clean, and the license is CC-BY-SA
The summary is "Trurl talks to Lee about some of his interests"
Hi, I'm Lee, and I'm here today with Trill.
Trill.
How do you spell that?
Trill, you are L.
T-R-U-R-L.
Trill.
It was Trill.
The robot, one of Stan's affluent stories, was called Trill.
And he destroyed everything, doing himself.
He went through everything alphabetically and creative.
Everything, one after another, right.
Starting with things beginning with the letter A.
Yeah, but the problem occurred when he reached the letter N.
And specifically, when he talks to the word nothing, right.
We were saying, I should create nothing.
No, nothing.
Yeah, anyway, to do that was destroyed.
Most on fortune.
Trill.
Yeah.
OK.
Yes.
Hello, Lee.
You're welcome to say what you're more mundane,
than I miss or not, as you may wish.
Yeah.
Well, my real name is Ben.
OK, Veronica.
We're sitting here in a suburban garden in Merton, I guess.
And it's a nice sunny August day.
It's a beautiful day.
Yeah.
We've had some late lunch.
And I've just got a cup of tea.
There's a cat called Tom Tom, just sitting.
Looking out of the garden.
My tea bag is in the tea, so it's not too.
There you go.
We can, yeah.
Would you like to start by introducing some of your main interests
and how you got into them?
Yeah.
I mean, I think my strongest abiding interests
is some mathematics.
So I studied that at university for a bit.
Among other things.
And then I sort of got more interested in it later
when I started tutoring, subject.
As a way to earn a bit of money.
But I was always interested in philosophy and politics.
And it's all of understanding the world really
and in general.
Along the way, I've studied different things.
And you pick up different insights from different subjects.
It feels like computing, obviously mathematics
are reachy-free for me.
I'm fairly tech and keep minded, I guess.
So I'm not so much a worthy person as a hands
and I don't know why you're using it.
You're a mean scrabble player, though.
Yeah, I didn't like scrabble when I first played it
because of the words and the frustration of playing.
But through forced exposure, I sort of at some point
realize that there was a technical element.
There was this line of attack, which was favorable
to my sort of way of thinking, which
you find yourself being quite competitive in games.
It's a funny one because I'm not a competitive person, really.
But I do push myself to achieve things.
I think that's the thing.
So I guess I take games probably a bit too seriously.
The main frustration, I get as much satisfaction
from beating someone at scrabble as I would
from solving a pseudocard puzzle.
So they aren't significantly different emotions.
But I'm not someone who likes to see someone else live
if you're a bopfling, I'd be happy.
And there's this go to other games or sports,
like tennis, snook, chess.
Well, yeah, I've put it mean all player.
And probably the thing I'm best at is probably snooker.
But I was coached in tennis as a teenager.
And I completely lacked the competitive instinct.
So consequently, I was not feeling sorry for my opponent when
they were losing.
And they call this choking intense.
Yeah, I think you need to have that desire
to enjoy defeating your opponent, which I completely lacked.
Do you think there's a better spectacodemia?
Well, I think it just depends on people's personality.
A lot of academics certainly department.
I studied in as a postgraduate for a while.
A lot of them were fairly hermetic and they just
wanted to be left alone to explore whatever peculiar
facets of geophysics that they have
and to find interesting.
Which was quite an inspiring thing in many ways.
But yeah, there are all sea other academics.
There was one in department, if you understood the knee,
it was very good at applying for funds and so on.
Certainly seen it in the scientific literature.
I've read some of it.
Some fields, you do see some really nasty disputes.
So it can be pretty vicious.
Yeah, at the end of the day, they're competing for funding.
So there is this rivalry going on.
I guess because of that, is it a mild dominant thing?
Well, geophysics is.
I don't know about dominates, but it certainly
were many women that were there were quite a few younger women
students and researchers in the department I studied in.
So what were your things that you actually studied
with the main things that you really spent a lot of time on?
Well, turned out I was quite ill-equipped to studying now.
So I kind of got the equivalent in chess
would be, I suppose, going to check maces in four moves or something.
Yeah, I didn't survive really studying that.
And I think at that time, it was a bit too narrow for me.
I'd probably been better off with natural science.
What I've learned about myself is I'm very theoretically oriented.
So the opposite of that would be what they call an empiricist
or your classic sort of either English scientist.
I'm going to maybe narrow it out or someone like that.
I've got complete to stand for.
I knew that at school when I studied science,
so I just couldn't see the point of experiments.
And I gave up physics at university for that reason as well.
I just couldn't stand the progressively mundane science lab.
I literally see no point to it whatsoever.
Yeah, I'm just interested in how things hold together.
It's a body of theory for a software engineer who is
having to do experiment after experiment to understand
different systems how they integrate together.
You cannot know that priorly before you actually get in there and stuff.
Well, this is something you learn in any technical discipline.
Yeah, I do think the hands-on knowledge is
something's the only knowledge there is really.
One of my very strong influences which I took from
my subsequent studies as an undergraduate
while socrates and I really sort of became interested in this character
who appears in the dialogues of Plato from ancient Greece
in the 4th century BC.
One of his statements which impressed me a lot was that
I don't know if it was a partly feature of the ancient Greek language,
but the knowledge was sort of identified with skill.
So that those two things and Socrates is always sort of
one that I was in particular sort of emphasises this very strongly and that's
sort of I think I've been born out by my experience in life that
you know and I think it I feel it's an under-appreciated thing
that actually yeah you do need to do things in order to
I mean anyone who's done programming things and mathematics and things you
will know that it's only one so you actually start having the problem that you
begin to understand what Bob made, what the challenges are.
You can sort of look at it from afar I think although
that should be like the devil's in detail and I think that's true of
you know more broadly I think of philosophical problems
can potentially be more fruitfully attacked with that that's a more
technical approach take Wolfram and his idea the a new kind of science
where the knowledge is coming through computation.
Well he's a great example of I think someone who's really loves to engage in
tinkering about really and you know he's got these insights from that about
the realm of computation and this idea that we've only explored a small
area of it and you know the kind of problems we tackle in mathematics are
are just this sort of subset of things that are actually
the half of these kind of convenient shortcuts which then forms the body.
The problem is the someone like Wolfram is that his
I imagine he has a fairly narrow domain of experience and expertise and the trouble then is that
this trappist you can easily over-generalize from that you could make a sort of analogy
someone I don't know they never used a hammer before or maybe no one's ever used a hammer
so someone sort of somehow creates a hammer like tool and they find it's really useful for
something and then you know it's not trying to use it for everything.
We all know that hammers are great for certain things but they don't solve every problem
anything. Yeah where have your I mean these implementations where if they let you what
what areas have you explored and even if they've not had any outcome that you could really
explain or point to but yeah what what areas have you kind of explored in there
studies or you thought well I think Gemini I started trying to explore sort of popular
questions I would say and a lot of them fill us off a cool question so
very things would interest me in certain questions of say politics so increase and I've got more
interested in technical things and yeah it's more just finding things where my approach will be useful
I think this is one of the things I love from my studies is that yeah there are certain
questions which are conducive to a one approach and others would be you know maybe a hammer
would be suitable and not other cases maybe you know something else you know so if you're a hammer
cut type of guy then you're going to be best off going off certain problems that will be appropriate
but frankly speaking how do you how do you where do you store these and the notes that you
make the knowledge you process they're all stored particularly not in pieces of paper that
around them they're scattered about right in my uh a boat and in emails I write you're going to
sing them out that works well enough for you so it's like why would you do something more
involved in that yeah I mean I'm a big fan of text files as well so a lot of text files
on the system you know and what text it's use yeah I mean just a note pad on wind
I mean I can't I don't screen on on right on your phone unfortunately yeah wind those texts
doesn't permit that so yeah but I'm yeah it tends to be whatever's to hand really so
I'm really not not very you're not you're not wedded to tools you're just like
whatever works and the ideas are more important there's honestly going to be a medium that they're
written in yeah songs it can be stored and so but yeah I'm going back to a question of
what I've explored one of the themes that I thought very interested in while it's the question of life
in the universe so this struck me as a question which could be conducive to a very theoretical
approach because but fairly obvious reason that it's kind of difficult to explore the universe
and gather evidence about iPhone other planets not everything else that is no more as a
thousand as a light is away yeah yeah that's kind of uh what kind of impossible literally um
actually so obviously there's Drake's equation which was really a rough information backing
of things yeah Drake's equations are rough and estimate the kind of yep favours one arts or another
or is it is it is it is it narrow to just be favoring it yes no answer should we be
no yeah definitely I mean yeah I ended up basically taking a quantitative approach to a whole thing
and I've read a very good book about which presented like a hundred odd in a different theories
about alien life it was written by song called web and yeah this is a very easy read to sort of
very and it appeals to me because it was a little chunks so I'm not sure we really want for big
tones so I like a lot and different you know the different ideas and he suggested look
read it why don't you construct your own model right of the galaxy whatever
well okay yeah um and after a while I sort of came round to eventually trying to do that so
yeah that was uh okay very fun exploration and yeah I think I think I gained quite a lot of insights
from that but it is a lot to potentially a lot to go into have you have focused on any like physical
systems on the planet earth yes yeah I mean a lot of subsequent to that I think I've gone
in a much more coming back to the data mathematical sort of analytical stuff and sort of trying
to do something practical so yeah I've looked at a lot of lot of things around you know any
data polling data politics sports you know I've always been a quite quite sporty games and things
so chess so you've looked at chess ranking systems yes yeah let's try so yeah I found out
various things about chess ranking system and yeah there are some some issues with it you know
these are fairly well in issues but I sort of found a few things out so it's sort of built up
load of techniques for actually sort of modeling modeling data really um we're statistical distributions
and things like that so yeah it turns out that that sort of practical applied mathematics is really
something a sort of niche I you know I'm pretty in the zone that we're there yeah and that
area you know would you say this is what keeps you infused and yeah going it's just literally
quite fun really for me I mean you do want to know things sometimes yeah yeah so and the
two of us jive get to the moment of a real tangible result like you've really nailed something that you
really get to yeah I do and unfortunately by the time you get to that stage it's become so
arcane right and you've utilized various techniques and yeah insights I mean I used to try to
sort of map where the ideas are come from you know in a sort of academic sort of mindset you know to
sort of keep your references and so on but yeah it does it does become is it only is it a bit
hard to structure it for someone else whereas it makes perfect sense to you yeah I mean sometimes
the victories are so subtle as well but sometimes he finds stuff out so for example with the chess
I actually found out that the very top chess players are under races by the rating system
they're actually far further ahead of everybody else than their ratings indicate so different
chess races were just very brief you you know sort of yeah it makes chess players based on their
result it it helps for it who's going to win any given match in the way yeah it sort of gives you
a sort of metric of who's the best basically and this Norwegian guy has been the top player
now for about 10 years what I found was happening was that because when you're very good it's
actually quite hard to win their chess game at the top level that they have a lot of dual stalemites
well it's not usually stalemate but oh what they what they just shake hands yeah they just give up
basically really nice that no one's going to win this game so maybe this is a bug in chess and maybe
the real revelation is that yeah well it is a bit yeah it is a bit um I mean the key real design
chess I mean with computers yeah that when they play games each other yeah I think some
over 9% of them games are drawn yeah more like 9% of them drawn yeah so yes it is really I think they
got this AI to play games itself and they made a rule that there was going to be no points
for a draw right so you've got this absolutely crazy getting where they were both just like
getting at it hangar and tons and sort of like one would try to sort of go to some incredible sort of
extreme attack on the on the king and then you know the other one would be one move away from
checkmacing their king but the game ended in a draw right anyway yeah um I think got interested in
chess to try to solve the ultimate chess problem which is how do you win from the opening
position there's a book all black to play and win so I became interested in this idea that
but a chess could be actually being a winning position from the start so technically you know you
could solve the game basically by having this incredibly elaborate book yeah I mean have
we could the rule book be the number of atoms in the universe is like yeah or would it be a finite
a more finite number yeah when you look into it it turns out that what they say in some
play we said it ultimately chess is a draw and yeah that's that's correct there's always a dream
yeah and we'd best play it obviously can be a draw as both for the humans who are not experts
that level of sophistication isn't a problem but yeah I put quite a lot of effort into trying to be
good at chess but I don't think I have I think my main strategy is try to distract the other
class and in some way so I never weird if I don't manage somehow to do that and I think I played
you once they almost got there but then you do what I was on up to yeah but I have gone a bit beyond
the level of um yeah I've and I knew nothing about chess whatsoever um there's actually all
extremely tactical game basically there's all this massive bag of tricks which you have to
learn really to be any good and you know it's like some kind of judo move or something
and you can just pull one of these out basically you want pretty much you know I mean most people
are so bad that you just have to I think you told me once that it's actually very useful to do
this practice is where they show a certain position and it's like how would you win from that
what we do next from that position yeah yeah so like puzzles basically you would see in the news paper
or you can but you can just train with them on why now you know it's upside in the way there's
it just is not any more really solving a mathematical thing so it's very much a human game
hmm it's like the limits of human perception the human theory human uh yeah all these things
the current top player is very much how's that view of it he rather sports you know um it's kind
of sporty himself so but yeah it's both I think I think it's both I mean I mean I I got to know
when you follow becoming trusted in a sport you can get to know this sort of cast of characters who
were play at the top level you know and you have a commentators and talk about them and they have
do interviews and so on and you can sort of get to know who they are and so on there's a lot of
uh extreme nerds and extreme um spurking us yeah oh you what and if you have the watch that
TV series the Queen's Gambit that's it but the the mind sets and dynamics yeah I mean they were
far too many that was the most unrealistic part of it there were far too many social dynamics and
what do you call it just colourful character in the main character yeah that was uh a glaring
but obviously inevitably to link this to what you've I think you've already expressed it's one
of your ever interests literature it I think there's a particular book that spans both the minds
by Nabokov yeah yeah you wrote a book about a sort of child prodigy in chess it's about is
he has memories growing up it he basically has a it has a kind of a breakdown because he's he gets
so obsessed with chess I mean this is a kind of fun an idea that the people are familiar with
from that I think from the chess world but what he's very good at Nabokov is these very vividly
recollected of sort of memories and subjective experiences of different coins and he has a memory
in particular of this man I think back to his childhood where he had sort of gone off from the house
he grew up in his big Russian estate as Nabokov did and he had to be the sort of the coachman
had to come get him and physically constrain him and sort of carry this boy back
you know just things like that oh god he's just quite vividly told and you can sort of
you know you can understand how that would have felt for a boy to to go to your experience but
well I won't reveal the ending of the book but it's some I think the breakdown occurs when he
comes to see at the board facing this particularly formidable opponent who's sort of risen from
nowhere to sort challenging he's sort of striving over this position on the board
for a moment he glimpses what he calls a fool horror of chess you know that the sort of
just the horrific complexity of the whole thing and if he never really recovers what was the
best of the book he's called the Lujin Defense right I think he Avocado explains that it's a
pun not so pun on losing but a pun on and the word illusion yeah he prefers so it hurts your
interest in books how's that developed over time and well let's see I mean the writer who really
got me very interested in literature was Edgar Allan Poe specifically remember I was working
in Cambridge at the time and I sort of had free time and very little to do so I would just found
myself going through books in the book shop near where I was staying and called a collection of
his short stories and I just sort of read what these in the shop and pass it just
absolutely taken by him and brought the book and then you know I'd just be spending evening
just reading this stuff and I just couldn't believe what I was reading I mean what I think about
Poe is a precision of his expression of his language I mean this is kind of a it's kind of a
generic feature of 19th century writing it seems and perhaps early writing as well that there's a sort
I mean there is some quite beautiful about the style often of some of these writers I mean
there are there are about what's as well it's um remember Hobbes stood out with that girl Thomas Hobbes
also for me and I'm I can remember that by my writing became inflected with all these sort of
weird 17th century and sort of expressions and stuff for a bit yeah it's a sort of language for thinking
I think and what what Poe taught me was that precise expression is very important
just I mean for yourself with much airing else because it's so easy just to
loosely and characterize an idea or for yeah of course often the expression of an idea isn't
a replacement for actually having the idea itself and if someone was to hear you second hand
explaining your view of if if my view of an idea they probably would not be able to
repeat the same idea that I actually had in my head because it's just I've expressed it in a certain way
and certain loose way yeah I mean I'm definitely a fan of vagueness and you know an
coercive exploration and yeah sometimes you you want to sketch something else and and it does
write about that some logic a bit there's something about it it has some of that quality for me
yeah did that lead you to other authors I wish there were other authors you know probably help me
appreciate other authors a bit like Shakespeare you know you know obviously has certain key stones in
it should can end up being underrated because they're so familiar that people just don't appreciate
the level of yeah skill and what's actually baked into the language baked into the ideas
and it just take it for granted I mean certainly struck me very immediately with Poe but yeah I
mean I do feel he's he's not appreciated not actually should be not perhaps canonized and I think
that's a lot to do with his totally disastrous personal life another thing in those days writing
yeah yeah he published a lot in gentleman's magazines and these are there any modern writers like
of of this century even don't want public might be something I guess no my favorite modern writer
is unquestionably modern ainess I think I enjoy his finances a little bit with science and
mathematics you're a very occasion but I don't know there's something off that and he grows a
voice he's much more modern you know simpler sentences which I'm speaking you know yeah there is
something like precise or what would you say you talk till three books by my name oh yeah well
obviously money is the famous one probably the best and then enjoy all his books I did I did
like information yeah he just very enjoyable writing about essays his and read to give a kind of
fresh example what's your what's your most recent like thing that you've really been into all right yeah
there's always so much yeah that I mean to that's going on so sometimes it's hard to really
find anything tangible I mean I think last year you were talking a lot about libertarianism
an economic like you're even you're asking me something that you would want to understand more
depth or so I think you're talking of some number of months ago about cryptocurrencies and various
ideas that you had around those yeah yeah yeah certainly yeah I got interested in um I was
brought up as a to be a socialist basically and with the sort of radicalization of the left
politics in Britain over the last ten years also I think I've just basically realised that
really ultimately I've just realised I've you know I'm not really of that persuasion at all and
you know I mean this is we're talking about politics obviously everything can be game said but
yeah so I think libertarianism is a nice way out of more radical political positions
um it's got its own idealistic strand as well so it serves us on substitute religion you know
if you if you're abandoning a faith that it were then there's an element of the flat but
yeah I think it says it's an idea which has a lot of merit I think um yeah I mean the politics is
it you know in a way my attitude to it is it's just politics I mean so you're you're kind of
more interested in the maths of it the stats of it oh well I was looking into economic yes yeah
yeah yeah I found that um various quite major things of how it was on a hundred years you can
even imagine so uh one of those things is um that actually people weren't really tax at all
before the 20th century anything like the extent they're having subsequently so that's quite interesting
I think my latest thought is that we sort of um I mean it the trouble is it's all
horribly controversial and people people get very offended if you when you say things so back then
yeah I mean we could talk about the the theories itself and but I mean it's more like
what's your how do you place yourself in relation to the knowledge and the maths and stats how does
affect your daily life or how does it affect your the way you think or yeah I mean I don't
know about my daily life but um um and until I can sort of start making his money out of it and
it's really just to to know things and um it's just sort of building up and understanding of you know
how I think something you've said to me is you know well there's a vast amount of knowledge
out there and published and being created all the time it's very difficult to
even if something staring in face to actually know what is actually a germane and relive and
yeah and pivotal piece of knowledge yeah yeah this is this is this kind of big kind of
epiphany thing just very recently that I've had which is yeah it's sort of putting
things together from why I've learned from sort of understanding different to me there's often
nuggets of information which are sort of lost behind the back of the sofa where and um
their significance is not really appreciated and you know we know this from technical
fields that you know some small thing can turn out to be the key to understanding
okay so you know you have to you just have to think of objects in motion you know in terms of
energy and then it's you know you have a kind of key to understanding of mechanics yeah yeah
yeah it just gives you an amazing so you know and I've actually sort of found this with different
things and um yeah I think because we're so advanced technologically I think there's a temptation
for people to think that we know everything and we've got everything now down we actually
understand you know we've got all the science and everything but what's become apparent to me is actually
I I've come to believe that we actually lack um certain key um keys to understanding
really properly various things and then I think the point is that there can be
the possibility to know is even yet greater than mankind is yet
um managed to achieve another sort of an economic train was the cryptocurrency thing and you
are you are kind of evaluating that there were different ways of trading things
yes it's that are not necessarily the bitcoins or whatever themselves but that they're derived from
some kind of stake and actually I I introduced you to the lightning network you realised that
some of your ideas actually had been realised already like independently of you you I think that
is a kind of validation that you independently kind of came up with something oh yeah it already existed
yeah I mean that happens quite quite you know quite spit so what's the disadvantage of being so
well read that you already know that and what's your advantage to having discovered it for yourself
yeah I mean I think it's it's inevitable result of always trying work things out for yourself and
rarely bothering to reach um what's already known very much so you're bound to to find out
things that people have found out already but the thing is like that's that's the only way that
I can make sense of so yeah that's that's how I like to okay to find things out and uh so one of
the things about this podcast is people can leave comments and they can ask questions or even record
their own response shows if people were to ask you to elaborate and certain things or give more
specific examples would you be open to recording further episodes of those sort of things
oh yeah yeah sure I mean very always good to have dialogue on um any any of these kinds of things
you know specific things or what gem or kind of picture that we've talked about cool yeah all right
so it's cool down a little bit yeah it's got a little bit chilly actually yeah so might be
time to go in uh the teas have been drunk and so goodbye from Lee and goodbye from Troll
You have been listening to the Hacker Public Radio podcast, at hackerpublicradio.org.
Today's show was contributed by a HPR listener like yourself.
If you ever thought of recording a podcast, then visit the HPR site to find out how easy it really is.
Hosting for HPR has been kindly provided by anhonesthost.com, the Internet Archive, rsync.net, and the HPR Community Content Delivery Network.
Unless otherwise stated, today's show is released under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-SA 4.0) license.